so hi my name is Joe brewer and I'm a
change strategist today I want to talk
with you about what I think is one of
the most important dimensions of social
change which is the role of belief
systems and in particular religious or
spiritual traditions for bringing
together people into cohesive groups
with many social psychological benefits
that are now well documented and also
for the spreading of ideas or more
accurately for the persistence of the
same kinds of ideas that are able to
last across multiple generations of time
the book that I'm reviewing today is
this one religion explained the
evolutionary origins of religious
thought bypass cowboy yay now this book
was written in the early 1990s but even
though it's almond though it's about 20
years old
it's still extremely relevant to what's
happening in the world today because
it's a work of anthropology that
establishes a key domain of human
behavior or human evolution if you will
that doesn't change very much and as a
building block for other kinds of
knowledge says book religion explained
has now become a foundational piece in
an entirely new field of research called
cognitive anthropology of religion and
cognitive anthropology of religion looks
at the relationship between ethnographic
field research cross-cultural studies
and human evolution the things that are
typically done in anthropology and
cognitive science in particular the
construction of concepts linguistic
intent or communication and the
psychology of ideas that spread from one
person's mind to another so what is it
that makes ideas able to spread easily
we're able to stay the same easily and
so this book religion explained offers
the first I don't know about the first
necessarily but for its time the most
comprehensive understanding or a
theoretical perspective for how
religious ideas are formed what makes
religious ideas so sticky and the minds
of people and able to
be transmitted from one generation to
the next so in many ways you could think
of this as a theory of cultural
transmission for religious ideas and
what boy a does that's just it's really
brilliant and I've I still refer back to
it even though I read this book more
than ten years ago it's constantly
coming back on my mind is he looked at
the make up of ideas and what makes
ideas psychologically sticky
what makes ideas something that's easy
to spread from one person to another and
what he found was that for all of the
key categories for everyday life so the
category for what it means to be a
person the category for what it means to
to be a tool that gets used you know
what makes something a tool or what
makes something a piece of furniture in
these kinds of categories in life that
the most powerful way to create an idea
that spreads is to make it both novel
and new kind of unexpected and
surprising enough that it catches
people's attention but similar enough to
what was already there that people can
make sense of it so for example he found
that with the category of person there
are several features or attributes of
personhood that are commonplace you know
people are you know you're a person if
you have a mind you're a person if you
have a body you're a person if you have
a consistent accumulation of memory
across time things like this and he
found that all supernatural concepts and
every religious system that he studied
in boy a as an anthropologist has looked
at hundreds of indigenous religions as
well as the major world religions he
found that all religious concepts have
the same basic recipe they take a normal
category like the category of a person
and then they violate one or two of its
expected behaviors the behavior of the
category of person but not more than
that so it's something that's novel and
surprising but so but still mostly like
what people are coming what people
expect
so for example for the category of
person what is it if you have a person
that
doesn't have a mind so you take the mind
aspect away from person the person
without a mind is what we call a zombie
what does a person that is a person in
every way except they don't have a body
that is a disembodied soul or a spirit
or a ghost so he took this idea that you
take the category of person and change
one of its attributes but not more you
get a novel and surprising concept and
people remember it want to talk about it
but it's understandable so people can
make sense of it and then he applied
this basic litmus test to all the
religious concepts and found that you
could create religious ideas that you'll
never find in religions so like imagine
there's a God who is all-powerful and
all-knowing but he immediately forgets
everything that he knows you're never
gonna find a category like that because
it's so nonsensical it violates several
of the tenants of what it means to be a
person that it just is nonsensical
people can't remember it they can't
communicate it so it just doesn't spread
so he takes this basic idea and then he
introduces an entire perspective a huge
lens of evolutionary thinking to the
field of religious study especially the
transmission of ideas across time and
this book is probably the best most
comprehensive analysis of this approach
and I highly recommend it for anyone who
wants to understand how religious
systems come into being how they change
in time and in particular the way that
that memes spread from one mind to
another to enable religious systems to
persist and to slowly and not to quickly
change in time so there you go religious
religion explained by Pascal boy a must
read for any culture designer who wants
to work with belief systems the spread
of ideas or religion in general enjoy